A Guide to the Bernice Kert papers FA236
Rockefeller Archive Center
Bernice Kert papers
1986-2003
Rockefeller Archive Center
Kert, Bernice Galansky
FA236
22.27 Cubic Feet 17 records storage boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The children of Bernice Kert donated her papers to the Rockefeller Archive Center by deed of gift dated March 16, 2009.
Biographical / Historical
Bernice Galansky Kert (1923-2005), writer and biographer, was author of The Hemingway Women: Those Who Loved Him (1983) and of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller: The Woman in the Family (1993).
Born in St. Louis, Missouri, Kert received her bachelor's degree in English from the University of Michigan in 1944. She continued on as a graduate teaching assistant in the English Department from 1946-1947. In 1945, she married Lt. Morley J. Kert, M.D., and they moved to Beverly Hills, California, in 1948, where they raised their three children. In addition to the two biographies, Kert published several short stories and wrote three novels.
Kert began work on her biography of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller in the late 1980s. In 1988, she received a John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation fellowship to support her research. She also was a scholar in residence at the Rockefeller Foundation's Bellagio Conference Center in April-May 1991. Bernice Kert's Abby Aldrich Rockefeller was published by Random House in 1993, and it was reissued in a paperback edition in 2003.
Scope and Contents
The Bernice Kert papers relate to her work researching and writing her biography of Abby Aldrich Rockefeller: The Woman in the Family (1993). The collection contains background research and reference materials, copies of archival materials, correspondence (1986-2001), research notes, manuscript drafts, and a series of recorded interviews with family members and other associates. The collection also includes Kert's diary for 1990, when she traveled to Russia to attend a conference on Hemingway.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- The Nelson A. Rockefeller Collection Masterpieces of Modern Art (Box 1)
- Alfred H. Barr, Jr.: Missionary for the Modern (Box 1)
- Old Money: The Mythology of America's Upper Class (Box 1)
- The Story of Spelman College (Box 1)
- Young in New York (Box 1)
- Valentine's City of New York (Box 1)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller: Catalyst for Conservation (Box 1)
- David Rockefeller Memoirs (Box 1)
- The Chief: A Memoir of Fathers and Sons (Box 1)
- The Rockefeller Women (Box 1)
- Edith Gregor Halpert and the Downtown Gallery. Volumes 1 and 2: Downtown, 1926-1940; A Study in American Art Patronage (Box 1)
- The Rockefeller Inheritance (Box 1)
- The John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation (Box 1)
- A Primer of Modern Art (Box 1)
- Rebels on Eighth Street: Juliana Force and the Whitney Museum of Art (Box 1)
- Study in Power: John D. Rockefeller Industrialist and Philanthropist (2 volumes) (Box 1)
- The Passionate Eye: The Life of William R. Valentiner (Box 1)
- John D. Rockefeller, Jr.: A Portrait (Raymond B. Fosdick) (Box 2)
- Those Rockefeller Brothers (Box 2)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's Letters to Her Sister Lucy (Box 2)
- Nelson Rockefeller (Box 2)
- Frederick Billings (Box 2)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Box 2)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Bernice Kert, Typescript Draft) (Box 2)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Box 3)
- Photocopies (Box 3)
- "Abby" Manuscript (Box 3)
- "Abby" Manuscript (Box 3)
- "Abby" Manuscript (Box 3)
- The Rockefellers, VHS tape (Box 3)
  Scope and Contents
  PBS Home Video
- The Rockefeller Family and Colonial Williamsburg, VHS Tape (Box 3)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Publisher's Proofs (Box 3)
- Bernice Kert Diary, Hemingway Conference in Russia, 1990 (Box 3)
  Note by daughter Katherine Kert Green that this diary is very special to her siblings and her.
- Research Notes and Clippings (Box 3)
- Research Notes and Clippings (Box 3)
- "Abby" Manuscript (2 c. f.) (Box 4)
- "Abby" Publisher's Proofs (Box 4)
- Loose Materials - Clippings, Publisher's Proofs, Correspondence (Box 4)
- The Clarion: America's Folk Art Magazine (Box 5)
- Fortune (Box 5)
- Antiques Magazine (Box 5)
- In the Sculptor's Landscape (Box 5)
- Artes de Mexico: Los Ninos Mexicanos, Pintados por Diego Rivera (Box 5)
- Time (Box 5)
- The New Yorker (Box 5)
- The New Yorker (Box 5)
- A Celebration of One Hundred Years - Pictures (Box 5)
- Life (Box 5)
- Life (Box 5)
- Life (Box 5)
- Manuscript (2 c.f.) (Box 5)
- What's What (Box 5)
- The Life of Nelson A. Rockefeller (Box 5)
- The Imperial Rockefeller (Box 5)
- The Rockefellers: An American Dynasty (Box 5)
- Photographs for Text (Box 6)
- Photographs (Box 6)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Correspondence with Children's Nurses, 1915-1924 (Box 6)
  Original folder title included notation "AARZ7."
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Correspondence with Children's Nurses, 1925-1935 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 6)
- Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 6)
- Babs Rockefeller (Box 6)
- Assistant File (Box 6)
- Rockefeller Lectures (Box 6)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Bernice Kert) - Photo number 10, Includes still images (Box 6)
- Good Old Modern: An Intimate Portrait of the Museum of Modern Art (Loose Photocopy) (Box 6)
- Chaim Soutine, 1893-1943, by Maurice Tuchman (Los Angeles County Museum of Art) (Box 6)
- Folk Art - Williamsburg (To Be Filed on Bookshelf) (Box 6)
- Publishers Weekly (Box 6)
- Avenue (Box 6)
- New Yorker Article (Loose Photocopy) (Box 6)
- The New Criterion (Box 6)
- Gertrude Vanderbilt Whitney: A Biography (by B.H. Friedman) (Box 6)
- Museum of Modern Art Bulletins (Box 6)
- James MacGregor Burns (Box 6)
- Profiles for The Nation (Loose Papers) (Box 6)
- Manuscript (Loose Photocopies) (Box 6)
- The New Yorker (Box 6)
- Sacks Harvard (Box 6)
- The Rockefeller Century (Box 6)
- Loose Papers and Notebooks (Airplane Tickets, 3 Notebooks, Guggenheim Fellowship Pamphlets) (Box 6)
- Letters - Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (2 c.f.) (Box 7)
- Notebook 1 - Prints by Americans (Box 7)
- Notebook 2 - European Artists (continued) (Box 7)
- New York Shopping Guide (Box 7)
- Guggenheim Foundation President's Report (Box 7)
- The Elements of Style (Box 7)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Box 7)
- The Troubled Face of Biography (Box 7)
- Photographs (9 envelopes) (Box 7)
- The Lucy Truman Aldrich Collection of European Porcelain Figures of the Eighteenth Century (Box 7)
- House and Garden (Box 7)
- Folk Treasures of Mexico (Box 7)
- Official Guide to Colonial Williamsburg (Box 7)
- The Legacy of Bessie Dashiell (Box 7)
- Providence: A Pictorial History (Box 7)
- American Folk Portraits (Box 8)
- Flora (Box 8)
- My Father's House at Pocantico Hills (2 Volumes, Typescript) (Box 8)
- American Folk Art (Box 8)
- New York Interiors at the Turn of the Century (Box 8)
- Nelson W. Aldrich Papers, Library of Congress Register and Index (Box 8)
- Newport Mansions (Box 8)
- American Indian Art - Taos Artists (Box 8)
- German Expressionist Sculpture (Box 8)
- German Expressionist Prints and Drawings (Box 8)
- Once upon a City (Box 8)
- American Folk Paintings (Box 8)
- American Painting (Box 8)
- Beatrix Farrand's American Landscapes (Box 8)
- American Furniture (Box 8)
- American Folk Art (Box 8)
- Milton Avery (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1986-1988 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, 1995-1997 (Box 9)
- Fitzgerald Conference, 1992 (Box 9)
- Rockefeller Lists and Travels - Finished (Box 9)
- Rockefeller Proposal, 1987 (Box 9)
- WGBH - Rockefeller (Box 9)
- Rockefeller - Permissions (Box 9)
- Rockefeller - Room 5600 (Box 9)
- Rockefeller - Correspondence (Box 9)
- Rockefeller - General (Box 9)
- Random House (Box 9)
- Random House - Business (Box 9)
- American National Biography (Box 9)
- Lucy Truman Aldrich to Abby Aldrich Rockefeller (Box 9)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to David Rockefeller, 1920-1938 (Box 9)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to David Rockefeller (Box 9)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to David Rockefeller, 1939-1943 (Box 9)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to David Rockefeller (Box 9)
- David Rockefeller, 1944 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - David Rockefeller (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to David Rockefeller, 1946-1948 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - David Rockefeller, 1945-1948 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to/from John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and Laura Spelman Rockefeller (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1901-1907 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1908-1920 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1921-1948 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - John D. Rockefeller 3rd. (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller to/from Laurance S. Rockefeller (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Laurance S. Rockefeller (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Laurance S. Rockefeller, 1930 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Nelson A. Rockefeller (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Correspondence - General (Folder 1 of 2), 1908-1924 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Correspondence - General (Folder 2 of 2), 1908-1924 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Correspondence - General, 1925-1933 (Box 10)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Correspondence - General, 1934-1948 (Box 10)
- David Rockefeller, Memoirs (Box 10)
- John D. Rockefeller, Sr. - Correspondence - General (Box 10)
- John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (Box 11)
- John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Laura Spelman Rockefeller, 1897-1907 (Box 11)
- John D. Rockefeller, Sr. and Laura Spelman Rockefeller (Box 11)
- John D. Rockefeller, Sr. - Laura Spelman Rockefeller, 1908-1910 (Box 11)
- John D. Rockefeller, Sr. - Laura Spelman Rockefeller, 1911-1915 (Box 11)
- John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - John D. Rockefeller, Sr. (Box 11)
- John D. Rockefeller 3rd and Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller (Box 11)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Trips (Folder 1 of 3) (Box 11)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Trips (Folder 2 of 3) (Box 11)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. - Trips (Folder 3 of 3) (Box 11)
- Fred Smith and Laurance S. Rockefeller (Box 11)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller (Box 11)
- Nelson A. Rockefeller (Box 11)
- Winthrop Rockefeller (Box 11)
- Williamsburg (Box 11)
- Bellagio, 1988-1989 (Box 11)
- Bellagio - Brochures (Box 11)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Correspondence (Box 11)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Items already Examined and Xeroxed (Box 11)
- Rockefeller Archive Center (Box 11)
- Nelson W. Aldrich papers, Library of Congress, 1861 (Box 12)
- Nelson W. Aldrich papers, Library of Congress, 1865-1873 (Box 12)
- Nelson W. Aldrich papers, Library of Congress, 1903-1911 (Box 12)
- Lucy Truman Aldrich (Box 12)
- Dr. Weiss (Box 12)
- Bayway, YWCA Dodge Hotel, Pocantico (Box 12)
- Artists and Art Critics (Box 12)
- Archives of American Art (Box 12)
- Bibliography and Research Tools (Box 12)
- Death and Afterword in MoMA (Box 12)
- Film Clips (Box 12)
- Genealogies (Box 12)
- Patrick Chasse, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- David Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Caroline Weekley, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- David Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Lucille Astaire, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Laura Chasin, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Abby O'Neill, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Ellen Harrison - David Rockefeller Gardens, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- David Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Bassett Hall, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- John D. Rockefeller IV, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Mary Barnes, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Eliza Cobb, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Peter Johnson, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Dr. Stebbins and Mrs. Stebbins, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- William Lieberman, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Spelman Prentice, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Blanchette Hooker Rockefeller and Eleanor Bradshaw, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Doklov, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- David Rockefeller and Franklin, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Fred Smith and Rodman Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Tom Armstrong, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Eleanor R. Bradshaw, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Dorothy Melle, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Abby O'Neill, Peter Johnson, and Fred Smith, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Jeannette Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Margaret Barr, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Tessein, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Monroe Wheeler, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- David Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- David Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Philip Johnson, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Laurance S. Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Philip Johnson and Monroe Wheeler, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Albert I. Berger Manuscript, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Peggy Rockefeller and David Rockefeller, Audio cassette tape (Box 12)
- Garden at Seal Harbor - 9 (Box 13)
- Houses, Gardens, History, Manhattan (Box 13)
- Interviews - General (Box 13)
- Mexican Arts Association - 7, Paine (Box 13)
- Museum of Modern Art - General (Box 13)
- Archives of American Art, Alfred H. Barr (Box 13)
- Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) Archives (Box 13)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), 1929-1932 (Box 13)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), 1933-1935 (Box 13)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), 1936-1938 (Box 13)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), 1939-1947 (Box 13)
- Rockefeller Archive Center - Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) - [Cultural?] Interests (Box 13)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 1-5 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 6-10 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 11-15 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 16-20 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 21-25 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 26-30 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 31-35 (Box 14)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller, Chapters 36-40 (Box 14)
- New York Times (Box 14)
- Photographs (Box 14)
- Reprints and Miscellaneous (Box 14)
- Providence Journal (Box 15)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and Diego Rivera (Box 15)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller and Folk Art (Box 15)
- Bernice Kert, Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1916-1928 (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1929 (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1930 (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1931-1933 (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1934 (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1935-1937 (Box 15)
- Winthrop Rockefeller, 1938-1950 (Box 15)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Miscellaneous Art (Box 15)
- Abby Aldrich Rockefeller - Diaries (Box 15)
- Notes (Index Card File), Loose Notes (Box 15)
- Notes (Index Card File), A-E (Box 16)
- Notes (Index Card File), F-R (Box 16)
- Notes (Index Card File), R (Box 16)
- Notes (Index Card File), R (Box 16)
- Notes (Index Card File), R, MoMA (Box 17)
- Notes (Index Card File), MoMA, Miscellaneous (Box 17)